NARRATOR:
In the beginning, God created
the Heaven and the Earth.
And the Earth
was without
form and void
and darkness
was upon the face
of the deep.
And the Spirit of God
moved upon the face
of the waters.
And God said,
"Let there be light."
And there was light.
And God divided the light
from the darkness.
And God called
the light "day."
And the darkness
He called "night."
And the evening
and the morning
were the first day.
And God said,
"Let there be a firmament
in the midst
of the waters.
And let it
divide the waters
from the waters."
And God called
the firmament "heaven."
And the evening
and the morning
were the second day.
And God said:
Let the waters
under the heaven
be gathered together
unto one place
and let
the dry land appear."
The gathering together
of the waters
called He "seas."
And He called
the dry land "earth."
And God said,
"Let the earth
bring forth grass
the herb yielding seed
and the fruit tree
yielding fruit
whose seed is in itself
upon the earth."
And the evening
and the morning
were the third day.
And God said, "Let there
be lights in the firmament
of the heaven
and let them be
for signs and for seasons
and for days and years."
And God made
two great lights:
The greater light,
to rule the day
and the lesser light,
to rule the night.
He made the stars also.
And God set them
in the firmament
of the heaven
to give light
upon the Earth.
And the evening
and the morning
were the fourth day.
And God said,
"Let the waters bring
forth abundantly
the moving creature
that hath life
and fowl that fly
above the earth
in the open
firmament of heaven."
(SEAGULLS SQUAWK)
And God created
great whales
and every living creature
that moveth
which the waters
brought forth abundantly
after their kind.
God blessed them, saying:
"Be fruitful and multiply
and fill the waters
and the seas."
And the evening
and the morning
were the fifth day.
And God said,
"Let the earth bring forth
the living creature
after his kind.
And everything
that creepeth upon the earth
after his kind
cattle and
the beast of the earth
after his kind."
And God saw that it was good.
And God said:
"Let us make man
in our own image
after our likeness."
The Lord God formed man
of the dust of the ground
and breathed
into his nostrils
the breath of life
and man
became a living soul.
And God brought unto Adam
every beast of the field
and every
fowl of the air
to see what he
would call them.
(BIRDS CHIRPING)
And the Lord said:
"It is not good
that the man
should be alone."
And He caused a deep sleep
to fall upon Adam.
And he slept.
And God made a woman
and brought her
unto the man.
This is now
bone of my bones
and flesh of my flesh.
So God created man
in His own image
in the image of God
created He him
male and female
created He them.
And God saw everything
that He had made
and behold,
it was very good.
And the evening
and the morning
were the sixth day.
And on the seventh day
God rested
from all His work
which He had made.
And God blessed
the seventh day
and sanctified it.
Eastward, in Eden,
God had planted a garden.
And He said,
"Go into the garden
I have made.
Tend it and keep it.
Of every tree of the garden
thou mayest freely eat.
But of the Tree
of the Knowledge
of Good and Evil
thou shalt not eat of it.
For in the day
that thou eatest thereof
thou shalt surely die."
And God blessed them
and said unto them:
"Be fruitful and multiply."
THE SERPENT: Eve
Eve
Hath God said
ye shall not eat
of every tree
in the garden?
We may eat of
the fruit of the trees
of the garden
but of
the fruit of this tree
God hath said:
"Ye shall not eat of it
neither shall ye
touch it, lest ye die."
Ye shall not surely die.
For God doth know
that in the day
ye eat thereof
then your eyes
shall be opened
and ye shall be as gods
knowing good and evil.
EVE: The serpent hath said
that we shall not die
that our eyes
shall be opened
and we shall be as gods.
Taste it.
There's no harm.
It is
disobedience.
EVE: It will make us wise.
NARRATOR: And the Lord God
called unto Adam:
"Where art thou?"
I heard thy voice
and I was afraid
because I was naked,
and I hid myself.
GOD: Who told thee
that thou wast naked?
Hast thou eaten
of the tree
whereof I commanded thee
that thou shouldst not eat?
The woman thou gavest
to be with me
she gave me of the tree,
and I did eat.
What is it that
thou hast done?
The serpent beguiled me
and I did eat.
Because thou
hast done this
thou art cursed
above all cattle
and above every beast
of the field.
Upon thy belly
shalt thou go
and dust shalt thou eat
all the days of thy life.
I will put enmity
between thee
and the woman
between thy seed
and her seed.
It shall bruise thy head
and thou shalt
bruise his heel.
Eve
I will greatly
multiply thy sorrow
and thy conception.
In sorrow shalt thou
bring forth children
and thy desire
shall be to thy husband
and he shall
rule over thee.
Adam, because thou
hast harkened
unto thy wife
and hast eaten
of the tree
cursed is the ground
for thy sake
in sorrow
shalt thou eat of it
all the days of thy life
thorns also and thistles
shall it bring forth to thee.
Thou shalt eat
the herb of the field.
In the sweat of thy face
shalt thou eat bread
until thou
return unto the ground.
For out of it
was thou taken
for dust thou art
and unto dust
shalt thou return.
(THUNDERS)
(BABY CRYING)
I have made a man
from the Lord God.
Thy name
shall be called Cain.
NARRATOR: And the meaning
of Cain is "possession."
Eve again bare a son
and his name was Abel
which means
"breath of life."
And the children of Eve
grew to be men.
Cain was a tiller
of the ground
and Abel was
a keeper of flocks.
At the time of the harvest,
they builded altars
and kindled fires
upon them.
And Abel brought
of the firstlings
of his flock
and the fat thereof.
And Cain also
brought of the fruit
of the ground
an offering unto the Lord.
And the Lord had
respect unto Abel
and his offering.
But unto Cain
and his offering
He had not respect.
Why art thou angry?
lf thou doest well,
shalt thou not be accepted?
GOD: Cain?
Cain.
Where is Abel, thy brother?
I know not!
Am I my brother's keeper?
What hast thou done?
The voice of thy
brother's blood
crieth unto me
from the ground.
Now art thou
cursed from the Earth
which hath opened to
receive thy brother's blood
from thy hand.
When thou
tillest the ground
it shall not yield
unto thee her strength.
A fugitive and a vagabond
shalt thou be in the Earth.
(WOLF HOWLS)
For dust thou
art and unto dust
shalt thou return.
My punishment is greater
than I can bear!
Thou hast driven me
out this day from the face
of the Earth
and from thy face
shall I be hid.
And I shall be
a fugitive and a vagabond
in the Earth
and everyone
that findeth me
shall slay me!
GOD: Whosoever slayeth Cain
vengeance shall be taken
on him sevenfold.
I set a mark upon Cain
lest any, finding him,
shall slay him.
NARRATOR: And Cain
left the presence
of the Lord
and dwelt
in the Land of Nod,
east of Eden.
And Cain knew his wife,
and she conceived
and bare a son.
In the generations of time
when his seed began
to people the Earth
there were born men
apt in knowledge and craft.
As Jabal,
the father of such
as dwell in tents
and of such
as have cattle.
They made vessels
out of the earth
jars and pitchers
by the skill of their hands.
And Jabal's brother's name
was Jubal.
He was the father of all
such as handle the harp
and play music.
And Tubalcain, also
an instructor
of every artificer
in brass and iron.
And they learnt the secrets
of the ground
that it
should deliver to them
its fullness and strength.
But the knowledge
of good and evil
was in all the people
of the Earth.
And God grieved in
His heart that men
followed the way of evil
and that
every imagination
of
the thoughts of his heart
was only evil, continually.
The Earth
disclosed her blood
and no more
covered her slain.
The deed of
Cain was multiplied
a thousand times.
And God said,
"I will destroy man,
whom I have created
both man and beast,
for it repenteth me
that I hath made them."
But the Lord gave Eve
another son
instead of Abel
whom Cain slew.
And Adam called
his name Seth.
And from Seth's seed,
through the generations
was Noah born.
And Noah found grace
in the eyes of the Lord.
There dwelt with Noah
his sons: Shem
Japheth and Ham.
And his wife,
and his sons' wives also.
And Noah was perfect
in his generations.
He was a just man,
and walked with God.
GOD: Noah.
Noah.
Noah!
Hearken now to my voice
and take heed.
Now shall I tell thee
the matter of my grief
and of what thou shalt do.
The end of all flesh
is come before me
for the Earth is filled
with violence through them.
And behold, I will bring
a flood of waters
upon the Earth
to destroy all flesh.
And everything that is
in the Earth shall die.
Make thee an ark
of gopher wood.
Rooms shalt thou make
and shalt
pitch it within and
without with pitch.
And this is the fashion
thou shalt make it of.
The length of the ark
shall be 300 cubits
the breadth
of it 50 cubits
and the height
of it 30 cubits.
With thee will I establish
my covenant.
Thou shalt come into the ark.
Thou and thy sons
and thy wife, and thy
sons' wives with thee.
For thee have I
seen righteous before me
in this generation.
Hey! Hey!
(PEOPLE LAUGHING)
(LOUD HAMMERING)
What is more stupid
than this?
A man building a ship
on dry land!
WOMAN 1: A devil is in him
and hath made him mad
and his sons with him!
MAN 1: When shall
the Earth see this again?
He hath the sea in his head,
and his house rides up
on the waves.
(PEOPLE LAUGHING)
Father, is it
indeed God's voice
thou hast heard?
For look,
there is no cloud
in the sky.
Not so much
as would cover a bird.
The Lord waiteth
upon our work.
Then what need
is there of haste?
Shall we not do it
little by little
under cover of night?
He demandeth
every hour of the day.
In our obedience
must be no delay.
Will you question
your father's understanding
or doubt his ways?
You should be ashamed.
Yet when shall they
be rid of the work?
All things wait for this.
The ground is unsown,
and the house is unmended.
Give me one
to make the roof good
lest when
the rain comes the house
will not keep it out.
But, wife!
Shem!
More pitch!
Ham!
NOAH: We have need
of more pitch!
(SNORES)
Japheth!
Take the bucket and fill it,
and our work is done!
Shem!
Ham!
Japheth!
GOD: Noah.
Come thou
and all thy house
into the ark.
I will cause it to rain
upon the Earth 40 days
and 40 nights.
Every living substance
I have made
will I destroy from off
the face of the Earth.
And of every living thing
of all flesh
two of every sort,
male and female
shalt thou bring
into the ark to keep them
alive with thee.
Two
of every sort.
NOAH: Wife!
Sons! Daughters!
Fear not. The Lord hath
spoken and said:
"Bring two of every kind
to keep them alive."
They have followed me
and trust us
to mind them
and bring them to safety.
They're good beasts at heart.
They will do no harm to you,
nor each other
for they know
of the waters that will fall
upon the Earth.
And God hath chosen them
above all others.
There are more yet to come.
Japheth, help them
find their way.
Ham, Shem,
load hay and grain.
Wife and daughters,
put oil into the lamps.
And get thy house aboard
the ark in order.
(THUNDERS)
NARRATOR:
And God shut him in.
(ANIMALS SQUAWK)
(ELEPHANTS CRY)
Is it the wind
that waileth?
No, wife.
It is the chaff,
which the wind
driveth away.
(PEOPLE CRY OUT)
The Lord hath taken hold
of the ends of the Earth
and shaketh it.
(ANIMALS SQUAWK)
They cry to be fed.
We have work to do.
Shem
care for the animals
with hooves that
cheweth the cud.
Ham shall tend
the camels, hares,
swine and giraffes.
Japheth,
the tigers, the lions,
the cats of all kinds.
What shall they eat?
Milk from the cattle
and the goats.
Milk? For beasts of prey?
They're only
great cats, wife.
Do you not hear them purr?
Be not afraid.
He will do thee no harm,
for harm is not in him.
Shem, the red hart
has not eaten of his corn.
Fetch him leaves.
NARRATOR:
The waters prevailed, and all
the high hills were covered.
And Noah only
remained alive
and they that were
with him in the ark.
When will the rain cease?
When shall we stand again
upon the Earth?
God has told us
it shall rain 40 days
and 40 nights.
But here we know
neither the day
nor the night.
We cannot measure
the time by sleep.
We sleep when we will.
When we are rested,
we wake.
The moon has no
waxing or waning
and the sun
no rising or setting.
We are without
knowledge of time.
Nay, but I know.
Since the time
we came into the ark
and the doors shut,
and the flood carried us
upon its waters
the days have been 20.
And two.
Twenty and two.
How dost thou know
what is hidden from us?
By what rod dost thou
measure the darkness?
By the beasts,
who carry the days
within them.
Even as the sun
and the moon divide
the seasons into hours.
I know the time
by the lowing of the cow
ready to be milked
and the cackle
of the hen when the egg
shall be gathered.
I have counted the days.
In 18 days, then,
we'll know the world
as before.
Not so. When the rain stops,
still the water
will cover the earth.
Neither shall we know
the world as before.
When the waters
are dried up
then we shall know.
We shall be alone
on the Earth.
No other life.
Where will the ark
have carried us?
In what strange land
shall we be renewed?
The Lord has put
the future into our hands.
(GOAT CRIES)
All things will be new.
(RAINING STOPPED)
(POUNDING)
(ROOSTER CROWS)
(ANIMALS SQUAWK)
(NOAH PLAYS FLUTE)
Raven!
NARRATOR: And Noah
sent forth a raven
to see if
the waters were abated
from off the ground.
Go forth!
And the raven went forth,
and flew to and fro.
Even until the waters were
dried up from off the Earth.
And the raven returned not
again unto Noah anymore.
Also he sent forth
a dove from him.
But the Earth
was still seas
as it had been
in the beginning,
before the dry land appeared.
She hath found no rest
for the sole of her foot.
For the waters
are on the face
of the whole Earth.
Eat of the grain
and renew thy strength.
For in seven days
I shall send thee
forth again.
And the dove
came in to him
in the evening
and lo, in her mouth
was an olive leaf,
plucked off.
Let us make
a rudder and a sail.
For now we know
that the waters are
abated from the Earth
and we can find land.
What sail shall
discover the winds,
and what rudder
find our course?
The breath of God
shall divide the waves
and his hand only
lead us into safety.
NARRATOR: The ark rested
in the 7th month,
of the 17th day
of the month
upon the mountains
of Ararat.
Hey! Hey, hey!
NARRATOR: And the Lord
said in his heart:
"I will not again curse
the ground for man's sake.
While the Earth remaineth,
seed-time and harvest
cold and heat,
summer and winter,
and day and night
shall not cease.
The waters shall
no more become a flood
to destroy all flesh.
I do set my bow in the cloud.
And it shall be for a token
between me and the Earth.
It shall come to pass
when I bring a cloud
the bow shall
be seen in the cloud.
And I will remember
my covenant which is
between me and you.
And every living creature
of all flesh."
NARRATOR: And sons were born
unto the sons of Noah
after the flood.
And of them was
the whole Earth overspread.
And the whole Earth
was of one language
and of one speech.
Now these are
the generations
of the sons of Noah.
The sons of
Japheth: Gomer
The sons of Shem:
Elam, Asshur
And the sons of Ham:
Mizraim, Phut,
Canaan and Cush.
And Cush begat Nimrod.
And Nimrod was a king.
And he set to build
a tower that would soar
like his pride.
A tower that would
reach unto Heaven.
And his people sang a song
as they built the tower:
"Who can bend
the bow of Nimrod?
Or put strength
into the arrow like unto
his strength?
Nothing is too mighty
for him to do
No power is greater than his
He hath taken the Earth
and made it his own
He stores up
the thunder and wears
the lightning like a jewel
The glory of Nimrod
shines beyond the sun
There is none
greater than he
in Earth or Heaven."
And the Lord came down
to see the tower
which the children
of men builded.
And He said,
"Behold, the people is one
and they have
all one language.
And this they begin to do.
And now nothing will
be restrained from them
which they
have imagined to do."
My bow.
NARRATOR: "Let us
go down and confound
their language
that they
may not understand
one another's speech."
Stand your ground.
Obey me!
Make good what has
been brought down.
Am I not Nimrod?
And my voice is
your commandment!
What words are these?
Babbling fool!
Madness is in his mouth!
You mock your
king's tongue?
Shall a monkey
gibber against me?
NARRATOR: Therefore is
the name of it called Babel.
There the Lord
confounded their language
and scattered them abroad
upon the Earth.
The Lord waited
10 generations for a man
called Abram to be born.
He was born in Ur
of the Chaldees.
And when he had
come of an age,
the Lord said:
"Get out of thy city
and thy country
from thy kindred
and from thy
father's house
unto a land
that I will show thee.
I will make of thee
a great nation
and I will bless thee
and make thy name great."
So Abram departed,
as the Lord had spoken
unto him
with Lot,
his brother's son
and Sarai, his wife,
whom he loved
and all their substance
that they gathered
and the souls
they had gotten
and they journeyed
like strangers on the Earth.
They journeyed not knowing
whither they went.
And yet the land
lay before them
as the Lord had promised.
And the mornings
and the evenings
pointed the way.
Come! Come!
GOD: The hills revealed it.
Lift up now thine eyes
and look from the place
where thou art
northward and southward
and eastward
and westward
for all the land
which thou seest
to thee will I give it
and to thy seed forever.
LOT: Shall we indeed
inherit this country
in peace?
For the Canaanites
go about the land.
The understanding of God
is not our understanding.
And what shall
be brought about
and how it is perfected
is not in
our power to know.
Only in the promise
of what shall come
can we prosper.
And in that trust
have we
pitched our tents.
Wife.
Abram.
My husband.
The sun has gone down.
We have laboured
until evening.
I bring my love beside you
in the tent
as day answereth day.
Let my beloved
come into his garden
and eat his pleasant fruits.
Behold.
Thou art fair,
my love.
Behold, thou art fair.
I have drawn
away from my beauty
as from a stranger
for the years
have gone with the
going down of the sun.
Your beauty
stands in a sanctuary.
The enemy falters
in the street
and sheathes his sword
in the marketplace.
Time
cannot pass the door.
The strong lock of
the door is love
and the key
is in my hand.
As the apple tree among
the trees of the wood
so is my beloved
among the sons.
H is left hand
is under my head
and his right hand
doth embrace me.
My right arm covers you
as the night
covers the day.
NARRATOR: But Sarai,
his wife, was barren
and she had no child.
Yet was the land before them
as God had promised.
And they pitched their tents
in the length and
breadth of it
from Bethel
to Kadesh and Shur,
even unto Egypt.
With Sarai came also
her handmaid
Hagar, the Egyptian.
They learned the wells
and fertile places
Five score.
and Abram prospered.
Six score.
Seven score.
(CROWD YELLS)
And when they came again
unto Bethel
there was division
between the herdsmen
of Abram's cattle
and the herdsmen
of Lot's cattle.
Let there be no strife
between thee and me.
And between thy herdsmen
and my herdsmen,
for we are brethren.
Our substance is too great
for us to dwell together.
The land is not able
to bear us together.
Is not the whole
land before thee?
Separate thyself,
I pray thee, from me.
lf thou will go left,
I will go to the right
or if thou go right,
I will go to the left.
There below us is
the plain of Jordan.
And that way I will go.
Toward the cities
of the plain.
The men of the cities
are wicked,
and sinners
before the Lord.
From here
the walls of Sodom
and Gomorrah are white.
But within the walls
is the darkness of men.
Many tribes
and their kings try to
claim their domination
and the city walls
are refuge and strength.
God is my refuge
and strength.
The plain is
well-watered everywhere
fertile with fruits
of the earth
even as
the Garden of the Lord.
That is the way I shall take.
And my way is another.
GOD: Lift up now
thine eyes
and look from the place
where thou art
northward and southward
and eastward and westward.
For all the land
which thou seest
to thee will I give it
and to thy seed forever.
Lord God,
what wilt thou give me,
seeing I go childless?
Behold, to me thou
hast given no seed.
I will make thy seed
as the dust of the Earth
so that if one can number
the dust of the Earth
then shall thy seed
also be numbered.
But Sarai, my wife,
is barren and she has
no child.
I am the Lord
that brought thee
out of Ur
of the Chaldees
to give thee this land
to inherit it.
Lord God
whereby shall I know
that I shall inherit it?
Take me a heifer
of three years old
and a she-goat
and a ram of
three years old
and a turtledove
and a young pigeon.
Divide them in the midst
and lay each piece
one against another.
But the birds,
they shall not be divided.
Now have I made my covenant
between me and thee
and out of
thine own bowels
thou shalt have an heir.
And Isaac shall
his name be called.
Yet know of a surety
that thy seed
shall be
a stranger in a land
that is not theirs.
Its rulers shall
afflict them
pangs and sorrows
shall take hold of them.
They shall be in pain
as a woman that travaileth.
They shall be tried,
like metal in a furnace
as also I shall try thee.
I will make
a man more precious
than fine gold
even a man than
the golden wedge of Ophir.
Go.
Abram.
Behold now.
The Lord
hath restrained me
from bearing.
I pray thee
go in unto my maid
according to
that law which says:
"When a wife is barren
her maidservant
may bear for her."
It may be that
I may obtain children
by her.
I give thee
my handmaiden
Hagar the Egyptian
to be thy wife.
Is it so
that the promise
of many nations
shall be fulfilled?
Even so
And Abram went in to Hagar
and she conceived
and when it came
near the time
that she should
bear a child
Sarai, her mistress,
was despised in her eyes.
Are you not tired?
Let us stay our hands
and eat and drink,
now that the sun is gone.
Fruits of thy kind.
Figs that are dry,
and dates and raisins.
But for me
the fruits that ripen.
Go away from me!
Why weepest thou?
I am ashamed.
For what cause?
Did I not say to thee:
"Go in to my maid
that I may obtain
children by her"?
Even so?
Now I am despised by her
that she carries
the child in her body.
I am but the grass
that is bruised
where she walks.
I look through her eyes
and see myself as one
who no longer lives.
The fulfilment
of the earth
passes to strangers.
And I am left
as I was never born.
But the child is thine
by thy maidservant
and by the love
I bear thee.
NARRATOR:
From the south, even unto
the plain of Jordan
came four warring kings:
The kings of Shinar,
of Ellasar
of Elam, and Tidal,
king of nations.
These made war
with the king of Sodom
and the king of Gomorrah
and the king of Admah
..and the king of Zeboiim
and the king of Zoar.
Four kings with five.
They joined battle
in the vale of Siddim.
The vale of Siddim
was full of slime pits
and the kings of Sodom
and Gomorrah fled
and fell there
and the victors
took captives and goods
and went their way.
And Lot?
And Lot,
my brother's son Lot?
He is taken captive.
Shall the land
that is promised to us
have no peace?
And my blood
be taken into slavery?
Eliezer.
My lord?
Summon Mamre,
the Amorite
and Aner and Eshcol,
his brothers
who are confederates.
And you,
my trained servants
born in mine
own house
gather at the tents.
Three hundred eighteen
we be.
How shall we prevail
against so many?
They have gotten the victory,
and left off watching.
I will divide us
against them by night
and smite them.
(MEN YELLING)
(SWORDS CLANGING)
(HORSE WHINNIES)
Blessed be
the most high God
which hath
delivered mine enemies
into my hands.
Thou art my shield
and my exceeding
great reward.
GOD: I am the Almighty God.
Walk before me
and be thou perfect.
Thy name shall
no more be Abram
but thy name
shall be Abraham.
For kings shall
come out of thee
and I will establish
my covenant
between me and thee
and thy seed after thee,
and their generations,
to be their God.
As for Sarai, thy wife,
thou shalt not
call her name Sarai
but Sarah
shall her name be.
And I will bless her
and give thee a son,
also of her.
And she shall be
a mother of nations.
Thy child.
By my maidservant,
and by the love
I bear thee.
The smell of my son
is like a field which
the Lord has blessed.
GOD: This is my covenant,
which ye shall keep
between me and you
and thy seed after thee.
Every man-child among you
shall be circumcised
as a token of the covenant
betwixt me and you.
Thou hast 24 score and 7
in thy flock.
By each pebble I know you
as good servants.
You are blessed among us
and are indeed our blessing.
My lord.
Behold. Thy son, Ishmael,
hath seven years.
Give him thy blessing,
I pray
that he may live
before God as
the first of thy flesh,
and thy only son.
Yet have I told thee
how it stands between
me and Ishmael.
For God hath said
He will bless Sarah
and give me a son also
of her.
Wilt thou indeed believe
what cannot come to pass?
The years have
gone by and the promise
is not fulfilled.
With Sarah, thy wife
the time of
childbearing is over.
Give Ishmael, therefore,
thy blessing.
Thou can hope for no other.
Shall the Lord speak
and Abraham not believe?
What is faith if it say,
"This thing cannot be"?
And as for Ishmael
God has said
"Behold
I have blessed him
and will make him fruitful.
But my covenant
will I establish
with Isaac
which Sarah
shall bear unto thee."
And so I wait
upon his will
even beyond the time.
NARRATOR: And Abraham waited
upon the will of God.
And God was silent,
as one who searches
the strength of a man.
Three years passed
and two more added
and Sarah and
Abraham grew old.
My Lord
if now I have found
favour in thy sight
pass not away
from thy servant.
We go down
towards the city
toward Sodom
where Lot,
thy brother's son, sits in
the gate of the city.
Rest yourselves,
I pray thee
under the tree.
And comfort ye your hearts.
Where is Sarah, thy wife?
Behold, in the tent.
I will certainly
return unto thee, and lo
Sarah, thy wife,
shall have a son.
After I am waxed old
shall I have pleasure
my Lord being old also?
Wherefore did Sarah laugh?
Is anything too hard
for the Lord?
I laughed not!
Nay
but thou didst laugh.
At the time appointed
I will return unto thee
and Sarah
shall have a son.
We are going
towards the cities
of the plain.
I will bring you
on your way.
Shall I hide from Abraham
that thing which I do?
Because the cry of
Sodom and Gomorrah
is great
and because their sin
is very grievous
I will go down now
and see whether
they have done altogether
according to
the cry of it,
which has come unto me
and if not,
I will know.
Wilt thou also
destroy the righteous
with the wicked?
There may be 50 righteous
within the city.
Wilt thou not spare
the place for them?
Shall not the judge
of all the Earth
do right?
lf I find 50 righteous
within the city
I will spare
all the place
for their sakes.
What if there be
45 such men?
Or 30? Or even as few as 20?
I will not destroy it
for 20's sake.
Let not the Lord be angry
and I will speak yet
but this once:
Peradventure,
10 shall be found there.
I will not destroy it
for 10's sake.
NARRATOR:
When the sun was down,
Lot sat in the gates
of the city.
And he lift up
his eyes and looked
and beheld two strangers
coming into the city.
(WOMAN SCREAMS)
(WICKED LAUGHTER)
(LAUGHING)
(WOMAN MOANS)
(MOANS)
What strangers are these?
Where are they from?
Two angels of God.
So fair they are.
So fair.
(POUNDING ON THE DOOR)
(POUNDING)
Where are they?
What have you
done with them?
Yes, bring them out
unto us!
Bring them,
that we may know them!
I pray, brethren,
do not so wickedly.
For these strangers
here with us are of God.
Better you destroy
all I possess
than any harm
should be done them.
Behold, I have two daughters
which have not known man.
Let me, I pray you,
bring them out unto you
and do ye to them
as is good in your eyes
only unto these men
do nothing.
This one fellow
came in to sojourn
and he will
needs be a judge?
Now will we deal worse
with thee than with them!
I cannot see!
Whatsoever thou
hast in the city,
bring them out
of this place
for the Lord
hath sent us
to destroy it.
Take thy wife
and thy two daughters
which are here
lest thou be consumed
in the iniquity of the city.
Escape to the mountain,
lest thou be consumed.
Look not behind thee.
(BABY CRYING)
(WOMEN CLAP)
The name of our son
shall be called Isaac.
Thy son
and mine.
God hath made me laugh.
All that hear
will laugh with me.
Who would have said
unto Abraham
that Sarah would have
given children suck?
For I have borne him a son
in his old age.
In him
are the stars
of the heavens
and the sands
of the seashore.
NARRATOR:
And the child grew
and Abraham made
a great feast the same day
Isaac was weaned.
Cast out this bondwoman
and her son.
Who has put this
into thy heart?
Did you not see how
he went among us mocking?
I have a great fear
there will come such
division in our people.
Like Cain and Abel again.
I beg you, cast out this
bondwoman and her son!
The son of this bondwoman
shall not be heir
with my son
even with Isaac.
What sayest thou?
He is my seed.
I will not cast out the lad,
nor thy bondwoman.
NARRATOR: But God said
unto Abraham:
"Let it not be
grievous in thy sight
because of the lad
and because
of thy bondwoman.
In all that Sarah
hath said unto thee,
hearken unto her voice
for in Isaac shall
thy seed be called."
And Abraham sent her away,
and she departed
and wandered
in the wilderness
of Beersheba.
Lord! Let me not see
the death of the child!
And an angel of God
called to Hagar
out of heaven
and he said unto her:
What aileth thee, Hagar?
Fear not
for God hath
heard the voice
of the lad where he is.
And God was with the lad
and he grew
and became a great nation.
ABRAHAM:
Here are the generations
of my fathers named
to whom God gave life.
It has fallen to me
that the past shall
not be forgotten
and after me
my son
also shall remember it.
By what descent
are ye come?
These are the generations
of which I am made
of Noah, who by faith
prepared an ark
to the saving
of this house.
Noah begat Shem
and Shem, Arphaxad
and after him was Salah,
who begat Eber
and his son was Peleg
the father of Reu,
who begat Serug
the father of Nahor
and Nahor begat Terah
whose son was Abraham,
my father.
Here are the names written.
And here shalt
thy name be also
Isaac,
son of Abraham
when thou
takest my place.
Put thy hand upon it.
GOD: Abraham
Abraham!
Here I am.
The night is filled
with thy voice.
Here am I.
What dost thou demand of me?
Thy son.
Thy only son.
What sayest thou?
Take now thy son
thy only son, Isaac,
whom thou lovest
and go into the mountains,
where I shall show thee
and offer him there
for a burnt offering.
Wouldst thou I do
even as the Canaanites
who lay their first-born
on fires before idols?
Art thou truly
the Lord, my God?
Thou knowest.
No!
Thou wilt not
ask this thing of me!
Isaac
take leave
of thy mother.
Mother, I am
going on a journey.
A journey?
We are going on a journey
of three days.
I am going
with my father.
What does thou tell me?
A journey unto
the land of Moriah!
Unto Moriah?
Why unto Moriah?
God hath commanded
that we go there
to sacrifice unto him.
Six days must
I wait for thee?
Mother, it is a little time.
I have waited for thee
until I was old.
The days are
precious to me.
Isaac, Isaac
What should I fear
if thou goest
with thy father?
Father
this was a city?
The city of Sodom.
Lot sat here in this gate.
And here
came the two angels
to him.
He overthrew these cities
and all the plain
and all the inhabitants
of the cities
and that which grew
upon the face of the ground.
All the inhabitants?
And lo, the smoke
of the country went up
as the smoke
of a furnace.
The Lord, our God,
must be obeyed.
All the inhabitants
of the cities?
The children also?
Were the children
also wicked?
Father?
Shall not the judge
of all the Earth
do right?
Call the nobles
to the kingdom!
None are here.
All the princes are nothing!
Father!
The thorns have come up
in the palace.
From generation
to generation it will lie
waste.
Ye shall stretch out upon it
the line of confusion.
Has it not been told
from the beginning,
God is He that sitteth
upon the circle
of the Earth
that stretcheth
out the heaven
as a curtain
and spreadeth
them out as a tent
wherein to dwell
that bringeth
the princes to nothing?
Ye shall blow upon them
and they shall wither!
And the whirlwind
shall take them away
as stubble.
My son
the Lord God
appeared unto me
and said unto me,
"l am the Almighty God.
Walk before me
and be thou
perfect.
Behold, my covenant
is with thee
and I will make thee
exceedingly
fruitful."
Come, let us
leave these ruins
and go from here
into the mountains.
In all things
we must obey Him.
NARRATOR:
Then on the third day
Abraham lift up his eyes
and saw the place, afar off.
The wood.
The fire.
The knife.
But where is the ram
for the sacrifice?
Father!
My son!
There is nothing
He may not ask of thee?
Nothing.
GOD: Abraham!
Abraham!
Here am I.
Lay not thy hand
upon the lad
for now I know
that thou fearest God
seeing that thou hadst
not withheld thy son
thy only son, from me.
There is the ram
for the sacrifice.
Behold, I have tried thee
like metal in a furnace.
I have chosen thee
in the furnace of affliction.
Now will I multiply thy seed
as the stars of the heaven
and as the sand
which is by the seashore,
innumerable.
ENGLISH - US - PSDH